<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
    xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
    >

<channel>
    <title>Webmonkey</title>
    <atom:link href="http://www.webmonkey.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>http://www.webmonkey.com</link>
    <description>The Web Developer&#039;s Resource</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 May 2013 17:29:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.4.2</generator>
    
    <item>
        <title>The Two Flavors of a &#8216;One Web&#8217; Approach: Responsive vs. Adaptive</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/the-two-flavors-of-a-one-web-approach-responsive-vs-adaptive/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/the-two-flavors-of-a-one-web-approach-responsive-vs-adaptive/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2013 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Igor Faletski</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61793</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[Responsive Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Visual Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Visual Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Visual Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Promoted]]></category>
		<category>Director&#039;s Columns</category>
        <description><![CDATA[﻿[Editor's note: The following is a guest post from Igor Faletski, CEO of Mobify, which provides tools for adapting web sites for smartphones and tablets.] You&#8217;ve probably heard people say we&#8217;re living in a &#8220;post-PC world.&#8221; What does that mean for web developers? It means that 30% to 50% of your website’s traffic now comes [...]]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled -->
<p><div id="attachment_53661" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="width: 590px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/tablets.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/tablets.jpg" alt="" title="tablets" width="580" height="434" class="size-full wp-image-53661" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A handful of the many screens your website must handle. <em>Photo: Ariel Zambelich/Wired.com</em></p></div>﻿[<strong><em>Editor's note: The following is a guest post from Igor Faletski, CEO of <a href="http://www.mobify.com/">Mobify</a>, which provides tools for adapting web sites for smartphones and tablets.</em></strong>]</p>
<p>You&#8217;ve probably heard people say we&#8217;re living in a &#8220;post-PC world.&#8221; What does that mean for web developers? It means that 30% to 50% of your website’s traffic now comes from mobile devices. It means that soon, desktop and laptop users will be in a minority on the web. </p>
<p>How do we deal with this tectonic shift in user behavior? We’ve moved beyond the era of m-dot or t-dot hacks, into one where responsive and adaptive design techniques rule the day &#8212; what the W3C calls a <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/mobile-bp/#OneWeb">One Web approach</a>. The key part of the W3C&#8217;s recommendation is that &#8220;One Web means making, as far as is reasonable, the same information and services available to users irrespective of the device they are using.&#8221;</p>
<p>For developers that means that taking a One Web approach ensures that not only does your site work on the smartphones and tablets of today, but it can be future-proofed for the unimagined screens of tomorrow.</p>
<p>There are currently three popular approaches to developing a One Web site: using a <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/01/take-responsive-design-beyond-media-queries/">responsive design</a>; client-side adaptive designs; and server-side adaptive designs. </p>
<p>One is not better or worse than the other; each has its own strengths and weaknesses and the wise web developer will consider the benefits and drawbacks of each before picking the one that works for their next project.</p>
<h3>Responsive Web Design</h3>
<p>Responsive web design is the most common One Web approach. The approach uses <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/01/building-a-responsive-future-friendly-web-for-everyone/">CSS media queries</a> to modify the presentation of a website based on the size of the device display. The number of responsive sites is rapidly increasing, from the <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2011/09/the-boston-globe-embraces-responsive-design/">Boston Globe</a> to Disney to Indochino. </p>
<p>A key advantage of this approach is that designers can use a single template for all devices, and just use CSS to determine how content is rendered on different screen sizes. Plus, those designers can still work in HTML and CSS, technologies they’re already familiar with. Additionally, there’s a growing number of responsive-friendly, open-source toolkits like <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/">Bootstrap</a> or <a href="http://foundation.zurb.com/">Foundation</a> which help simplify the process of building responsive sites. </p>
<p>On the other hand, there are few shortcuts to a sound responsive design. To go responsive, organizations often have to undertake a complete site rebuild. </p>
<p>The design and testing phase can be quite fussy, as it can be difficult to customize the user experience for every possible device or context. We&#8217;ve all seen responsive site layouts that look like a bunch of puzzle pieces that don&#8217;t quite fit together. Responsive web design works best in combination with a mobile-first approach, where the mobile use case is prioritized during development. <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/03/video-progressive-enhancement-2-0/">Progressive enhancement</a> is then used to address tablet and desktop use cases.</p>
<p>Performance can also be a bugbear for responsive sites. At Mobify, we recently completed an analysis of 15 popular responsive e-commerce sites. Among these sites, the home pages loaded an average of 87 resources and 1.9 MB of data. Some responsive pages were as <a href="https://www.evernote.com/shard/s25/sh/c9f91915-af74-42b2-8771-ecfd37768225/3cd545176d8acff830daf5b1a3d1d3d6/res/3329c9b6-a9da-468c-8ffe-80c5bd1138ab/skitch.png">big as 15MB</a>.</p>
<p>The numbers are that high because a responsive approach covers all devices. Your user is only using one device, but they have to wait for all of the page elements and resources to load before they can use it. Put simply, performance affects your bottom line. On smartphones, the conversion rate <a href="http://www.webperformancetoday.com/2011/11/23/case-study-slow-page-load-mobile-business-metrics/">drops by an extra 3.5 percent</a> when users have to wait just one second. By the three second mark, <a href="http://www.strangeloopnetworks.com/resources/infographics/web-performance-and-user-expectations/website-abandonment-happens-after-3-seconds/">57 percent of users will have left your site completely</a>.</p>
<p>While responsive design is fast becoming the de facto standard, it also creates new challenges for online businesses, including how to handle images, how to optimize mobile performance and often means sites need to be rebuilt from the ground up with a mobile first approach.</p>
<h3>Client-Side Adaptive</h3>
<p>Adaptive design builds on the principles of responsive design to deliver user experiences that are targeted at specific devices and contexts. It uses JavaScript to enrich websites with advanced functionality and customization. For example, adaptive websites deliver Retina-quality images only to Retina displays (such as the new iPad) while standard-definition displays receive lower-quality images. </p>
<p>There are two approaches to adaptive design &#8212; one where the adaptations occur on the client side, in the user’s browser, and another where the web server does the heavy lifting of detecting various devices and loading the correct template. Examples of client-side adaptive sites include Threadless and ideeli. One of the strengths of the adaptive templating approach is the ability to reuse one set of HTML and JavaScript across devices, simplifying change management and testing.</p>
<p>A client-side adaptive approach means you don&#8217;t have to rebuild your site from the ground up. Instead you can build on existing content while still delivering a mobile-responsive layout. For expert developers, this approach also enables you to specifically target particular devices or screen resolutions. For example, for many of Mobify’s online fashion retail clients, 95% of their mobile traffic comes from iPhones. Client-side adaptive means they can optimize specifically for Apple smartphones. </p>
<p>Unlike responsive design, adaptive templates ensure that only the required resources are loaded by the client’s device. Because device and feature detection is shifted to the mobile device itself, CDN networks like Akamai and Edgecast can use most of their caching functionality without disrupting the user experience.</p>
<p>The client-side adaptive approach has a higher barrier to entry than responsive design. Developers need to have a solid grasp of JavaScript to use this technique. It also depends on a site’s existing templates as the foundation. Finally, because the client-side adaptations are a kind of layer on top of your existing code base, you need to maintain them as your site as a whole evolves. </p>
<h3>Server-Side Adaptive</h3>
<p>We can achieve the server-side adaptive approach in a variety of ways, through server-side plugins and custom user agent detection. Sites that use server-side adaptive include Etsy, One Kings Lane and OnlineShoes.com.</p>
<p>Why choose server-side adaptive? It typically offers distinct templates for each devices, enabling more customization, and it keeps device-detection logic on the server, enabling smaller mobile pages that load faster. Additionally, there are numerous server-side plugins available for common CMSs and eCommerce systems such as Magneto.</p>
<p>This approach isn&#8217;t for the faint of heart&#8211;it typically requires significant changes to your back-end systems, which can result in a lengthy (and costly) implementation. The requirement to manage multiple templates raises ongoing maintenance costs. Finally, this approach can encounter performance issues when servers are under heavy load. When mobile user agent detection is performed on the server, a lot of common caching mechanisms deployed by CDNs like Akamai need to be turned off. This can result in a slower user experience for mobile and desktop visitors.</p>
<p>Of course, many companies are still wrestling with the basics of responsive, and they’re not ready to confront the more sophisticated flavors of adaptive. Increasingly competition and mobile traffic, however, will drive more and more organizations to kick the tires on all three approaches, and pick the one that works best for their users.</p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/the-two-flavors-of-a-one-web-approach-responsive-vs-adaptive/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>11</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Internet Explorer 10 Doubles Its Desktop Market Share</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/internet-explorer-10-doubles-market-share/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/internet-explorer-10-doubles-market-share/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 16:05:39 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61774</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[Browsers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IE10]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[External]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/netmarketshare-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/netmarketshare.jpg" alt="Internet Explorer 10 Doubles Its Desktop Market Share" /></div>That's great news for web developers, but sadly, according to NetMarketShare's browser stats, IE 10 use still trails behind the 12-year-old IE 6.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled --><div id="attachment_61775" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 590px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/netmarketshare.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/netmarketshare.jpg" alt="" title="netmarketshare" width="580" height="199" class="size-full wp-image-61775" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">NetMarketShare&#8217;s browser stats for April 2013. <em>Image: Screenshot/Webmonkey</em></p></div></p>
<p>Microsoft&#8217;s Internet Explorer 10 saw a meteoric rise in market share last month, jumping from 2.93 percent in March to 6.22 percent in April, <a href="http://www.netmarketshare.com/browser-market-share.aspx?qprid=2&amp;qpcustomd=0">according to NetMarketShare</a>. </p>
<p>Some of IE 10&#8242;s growth might be attributable to more Windows 8 machines coming online, but it also comes close on the heels of the <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/02/internet-explorer-10-arrives-on-windows-7/">release of Internet Explorer 10 for Windows 7</a>. </p>
<p>As we noted in our review, <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/10/review-internet-explorer-10-bests-the-competition-on-windows-8-tablets/">IE 10 is a huge step forward</a> for Microsoft’s oft-maligned browser, bringing much better web standards support and considerable speed improvements over IE 9. And there&#8217;s plenty to like even on Windows 7 where Microsoft claims users should see a 20 percent increase in performance over IE 9, as well as better battery life on Windows 7 laptops.</p>
<p>While web developers should be happy to see IE 10 gaining some ground given its vastly superior web standards support and speed compared to previous releases, looking at the bigger browser share picture is still disheartening. While IE 10 use may have doubled last month, it still trails IE 6 use worldwide. </p>
<p>The most widely used version of IE on the web remains IE 8, which, while much better than IE 6, still has next to no support for modern web development tools like HTML5 and CSS 3. </p>
<p>As always, <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/03/video-progressive-enhancement-2-0/">progressive enhancement</a> and feature-detection tools like <a href="http://modernizr.com/">Modernizr</a> are your friends when it comes to older versions of IE.</p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/internet-explorer-10-doubles-market-share/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>2</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>WebRTC, Online Code Editor Team Up for Real-Time Coding</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/webrtc-online-code-editor-team-up-for-real-time-coding/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/webrtc-online-code-editor-team-up-for-real-time-coding/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 14:20:54 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61766</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[Programming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Web Apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WebRTC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Promoted]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/codassium_screen-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/codassium_screen.jpg" alt="WebRTC, Online Code Editor Team Up for Real-Time Coding" /></div>WebRTC is still in its infancy, but developers are already building cool apps around WebRTC's real-time video chat. Codassium is one such app that combines WebRTC video chat with a code editor for better way to conduct remote interviews, review code or do some remote pair programming.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled -->
<p><div id="attachment_61768" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 590px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/codassium_screen.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/codassium_screen.jpg" alt="" title="codassium_screen" width="580" height="272" class="size-full wp-image-61768" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Collaborating with Codassium <em>Image: <a href="http://codassium.com/">codassium.com</a></em>.</p></div>It&#8217;s still going to be some time before WebRTC technology starts to deliver cool apps, but even today developers are quickly moving from the realm of cool WebRTC experiments, like the <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/02/google-mozilla-team-up-for-skype-killing-video-call-demo/">Mozilla/Google phone call demo</a>, to useful apps like <a href="http://codassium.com/">Codassium</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.webrtc.org/">WebRTC</a> is a proposed standard &#8212; currently being refined by the W3C &#8212; with the goal of providing a web-based set of tools that any device can use to share audio, video and data in real time. It&#8217;s still in the early stages, but WebRTC has the potential to supplant Skype, Flash and many native apps with web-based alternatives that work on any device.</p>
<p>Codassium uses WebRTC to bring together WebRTC-based video chat and <a href="http://ace.ajax.org/">Mozilla&#8217;s Ace code editor</a>. The result is what <a href="http://wreally.com/">Wreally Studios</a>, creators of Codassium, call &#8220;a better way to conduct remote interviews.&#8221; Of course Codassium could be used for more than just interviews &#8212; think code reviews, remote pair programming or even just discussing code with remote employees.</p>
<p>To use Codassium you&#8217;ll need to be using a web browser that supports WebRTC &#8212; recent versions of Firefox and Chrome will both work. Head on over to <a href="http://codassium.com/">Codassium</a>, click the Start button and allow the site to access your camera and microphone. Once the video chat and Ace editor load, just click the Invite button and send the resulting link to the person you&#8217;d like to work with.</p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/05/webrtc-online-code-editor-team-up-for-real-time-coding/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Video: What Does 10 Petabytes of Data Look Like?</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/video-what-does-10-petabytes-look-like/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/video-what-does-10-petabytes-look-like/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 16:01:31 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61753</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[Web Basics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet Archive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wayback]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internal]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/peta-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/peta-660x365.jpg" alt="Video: What Does 10 Petabytes of Data Look Like?" /></div>The Internet Archive is on a mission to archive the web. All of it. Filmmaker Jonathan Minard's documentary, Internet Archive, takes a behind the scenes look at how (and why) the Internet Archive's efforts are preserving the web as we know it.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled --><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/59207751" width="580" height="326" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe></p>
<p>The Internet Archive&#8217;s <a href="http://archive.org/web/web.php">Wayback Machine</a> is deceptively simple &#8212; plug in a website and you can see copies of it over time. </p>
<p>What you don&#8217;t see is the massive amount of effort, data and storage necessary to capture and maintain those archives. Filmmaker Jonathan Minard&#8217;s documentary <a href="http://vimeo.com/59207751">Internet Archive</a> takes a behind the scenes look at how (and why) the Internet Archive&#8217;s efforts are preserving the web as we know it.</p>
<p>The interview with Brewster Kahle, founder of the Internet Archive, especially offers a look at not just the idea behind the archive, but the actual servers that hold the 10 petabytes of archived websites, books, movies, music, and television broadcasts that the Internet Archive currently stores. </p>
<p>For more on the documentary, <a href="http://vimeo.com/59207751">head over to Vimeo</a>. You can learn more about the <a href="http://archive.org/index.php">Internet Archive</a> on the group&#8217;s website.</p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/video-what-does-10-petabytes-look-like/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>1</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>The Very First Website Returns to the Web</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/the-very-first-website-returns-to-the-web/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/the-very-first-website-returns-to-the-web/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 13:09:54 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61742</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[HTML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Web Basics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[history]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[External]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/WWW_logo_by_Robert_Cailliau_200_0-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/WWW_logo_by_Robert_Cailliau_200_0.jpg" alt="The Very First Website Returns to the Web" /></div>CERN has resurrected the very first webpage that Tim Berners-Lee and the WWW team ever put online, offering a hands-on look at the proto-web.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled --><div id="attachment_61746" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="width: 230px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/WWW_logo_by_Robert_Cailliau_200_0.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/WWW_logo_by_Robert_Cailliau_200_0.jpg" alt="" title="WWW_logo_by_Robert_Cailliau_200_0" width="220" height="167" class="size-full wp-image-61746" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Robert Cailliau&#8217;s original WWW logo. <em>Image: <a href="http://first-website.web.cern.ch/">CERN</a></em>.</p></div>
<p>Twenty years ago today CERN <a href="https://cds.cern.ch/record/1164399">published a statement</a> that made the World Wide Web freely available to everyone. To celebrate that moment in history, CERN is bringing the very first website back to life at its original URL.</p>
<p>If you&#8217;d like to see the very first webpage Tim Berners-Lee and the WWW team ever put online, point your browser to <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/TheProject.html">http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/TheProject.html</a>. </p>
<p>For years now that URL has simply redirected to the root info.cern.ch site. But, because we all know <a href="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html">cool URIs don&#8217;t change</a>, CERN has brought it back to life. Well, sort of anyway. The site has been reconstructed from an archive hosted on the W3C site, so what you&#8217;re seeing is a 1992 copy of the first website. Sadly this is, thus far, the earliest copy anyone can find, though the team at CERN is hoping to turn up an older copy.</p>
<p>Be sure to view the source of the first webpage. You&#8217;ll find quite a few things about early HTML that have long since changed &#8212; like the use of <code>&lt;HEADER&gt;</code> instead of <code>&lt;HEAD&gt;</code> or the complete absence of a root <code>&lt;HTML&gt;</code> tag. There&#8217;s also a trace of Berners-Lee&#8217;s <a href="http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/WorldWideWeb.html">famous NeXT machine</a> in the <code>&lt;NEXTID N="55"&gt;</code> tag.</p>
<p>CERN has big plans for the original website, starting with bringing the rest of the pages back online. &#8220;Then we will look at the first web servers at CERN and see what assets from them we can preserve and share,&#8221; writes CERN&#8217;s Dan Noyes. &#8220;We will also sift through documentation and try to restore machine names and IP addresses to their original state.&#8221;</p>
<p>In the mean time, have a look at the web&#8217;s <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/Bugs.html">original todo list</a> and read more about <a href="http://markboulton.co.uk/journal/firstwebsite">the project to restore the first website</a> over on Mark Boulton&#8217;s blog.</p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/the-very-first-website-returns-to-the-web/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Chrome Extension Opens MS Office Docs in the Browser</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/chrome-extension-opens-ms-office-docs-in-the-browser/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/chrome-extension-opens-ms-office-docs-in-the-browser/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2013 17:01:49 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61729</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[Browsers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[External]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Promoted]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/chromeoffice-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/chromeoffice.jpg" alt="Chrome Extension Opens MS Office Docs in the Browser" /></div>Google is porting its Microsoft Office Viewer from Chrome OS to Chrome on Mac and Windows, offering users an easy and more secure way to view office files -- right in the web browser. Unfortunately the Office Viewer for Google Chrome is still a bit rough around the edges.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled --><div id="attachment_61730" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 590px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/chromeoffice.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/chromeoffice.jpg" alt="" title="chromeoffice" width="580" height="355" class="size-full wp-image-61730" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Viewing MS Office docs in Chrome. <em>Image: Screenshot/Webmonkey</em></p></div></p>
<p>Google Chrome OS users have long enjoyed the ability to open Microsoft Office documents right in the web browser. Now Google is expanding its MS Office support to <a href="http://chrome.blogspot.co.uk/2013/04/a-speedy-more-secure-way-to-view.html">include Chrome on Windows and Mac</a> as well.</p>
<p>The new <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/chrome-office-viewer-beta/gbkeegbaiigmenfmjfclcdgdpimamgkj?hl=en">Office Viewer beta</a> is an extension for Google Chrome. You&#8217;ll need to be using Chrome 27 or better (currently in the beta channel), but provided you&#8217;re willing to use the prerelease version, you can <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/chrome-office-viewer-beta/gbkeegbaiigmenfmjfclcdgdpimamgkj?hl=en">install the new Office Viewer</a> (also a beta release) from the Chrome Store.</p>
<p>The new extension can open most Microsoft Office files including .doc, .docx, .xls, .xlsx, .ppt, .pptx. The interface is very similar to the existing PDF view in Chrome and comes from <a href="http://www.quickoffice.com/">QuickOffice</a>, which Google acquired last year.</p>
<p>The main downside to the new plugin is that it&#8217;s definitely still a beta &#8212; very buggy and rough around the edges. In my testing two very simple spreadsheets simply didn&#8217;t open and selecting text in .docx Word documents was hit or miss; sometimes it worked, other times it was as if the document had been converted to an image. </p>
<p>On the plus side your MS Office files open in a specialized sandbox which protects you from any malware and viruses lurking in the files.</p>
<p>Still, there are enough rough edges that Chrome&#8217;s Office plugin isn&#8217;t ready for prime time. While it&#8217;s a necessity on Chrome OS, which has no Microsoft Office suite, everywhere else you&#8217;re probably better off using Google Drive to view files when you&#8217;re online (assuming you want to use Google services, Zoho Docs works well if you don&#8217;t), and Microsoft Office or Open/Libre Office when you&#8217;re not. </p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/chrome-extension-opens-ms-office-docs-in-the-browser/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Nginx Server Speeds Up the Tubes With &#8216;SPDY&#8217; Support</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/nginx-speeds-up-the-tubes-with-spdy-support/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/nginx-speeds-up-the-tubes-with-spdy-support/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 17:16:34 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61711</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[servers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nginx]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SPDY]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internal]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/curves_by_wetsun_flickr-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/curves_by_wetsun_flickr.jpg" alt="Nginx Server Speeds Up the Tubes With &#8216;SPDY&#8217; Support" /></div>The Nginx server is the latest in what's now a long list of companies and tools supporting the proposed HTTP successor, SPDY. SPDY promises to speed up website load times by up to 40 percent, which makes it a perfect fit for the already fast and lightweight Nginx server.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled --><div id="attachment_61713" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 590px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/curves_by_wetsun_flickr.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/curves_by_wetsun_flickr.jpg" alt="" title="curves_by_wetsun_flickr" width="580" height="330" class="size-full wp-image-61713" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Tubes so fast they&#8217;re blurry. <em>Image: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/wetsun/32981430/">Wetsun/Flickr</a></em>.</p></div></p>
<p>The team behind Nginx (pronounced engine-ex) have <a href="http://nginx.org/#2013-04-24">released version 1.4</a>, which brings a number of new features, most notably support for the SPDY protocol.</p>
<p>SPDY, the HTTP replacement, promises to speed up website load times by up to 40 percent. Given that Nginx is the <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/01/open-source-upstart-nginx-surpasses-microsoft-server/">second most popular server on the web</a> &#8212; powering big name sites like Facebook and WordPress &#8212; the new SPDY support should prove a boon for the nascent protocol. Apache, still far and away the most popular server on the web, also has a <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/spdy/mod_spdy/">mod_spdy module</a>.</p>
<p>SPDY support should also help make Nginx more appealing, not that it needs much help. Nginx&#8217;s winning combination of lightweight and fast have made it the darling of the web in recent years with everyone from Facebook to Dropbox relying on it in one form or another. </p>
<p>Indeed, part of Nginx&#8217;s success lies in its versatility. The server can be used for everything from a traditional high performance web server to a load balancer, a caching engine, a mail proxy or an HTTP streaming server. </p>
<p>It&#8217;s worth noting that if you&#8217;re installing Nginx 1.4 on a Linux server directly from your distro&#8217;s repos the new SPDY support may not be enabled. See the Nginx documentation for <a href="http://nginx.org/en/docs/http/ngx_http_spdy_module.html">instructions on building from source with SPDY support enabled</a>.</p>
<p>SPDY isn&#8217;t the only thing new in Nginx 1.4, there&#8217;s also support for proxying WebSocket connections and a new <a href="http://nginx.org/en/docs/http/ngx_http_gunzip_module.html">Gunzip module</a> that decompresses gzip files for clients that do not support gzip encoded files.</p>
<p>For more details and to grab the latest Nginx source, head on over to the <a href="http://nginx.org/en/download.html">Nginx website</a>.</p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/nginx-speeds-up-the-tubes-with-spdy-support/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>1</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Experimental CSS Shaders Bring Photoshop Filters to the Web</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/experimental-css-shaders-bring-photoshop-filters-to-the-web/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/experimental-css-shaders-bring-photoshop-filters-to-the-web/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 12:45:50 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61704</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[CSS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Web Standards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[External]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/blendmodes-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/blendmodes.jpg" alt="Experimental CSS Shaders Bring Photoshop Filters to the Web" /></div>Adobe wants the next Instagram to be a web app. The company is hard at work porting filters and effects from Photoshop to the web. The latest experimental builds of both Chrome and Safari add support for the company's proposed CSS fragment shaders -- think Photoshop blending modes like multiply or overlay right in your browser.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled -->
<p><div id="attachment_61706" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 590px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/blendmodes.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/blendmodes.jpg" alt="" title="blendmodes" width="580" height="400" class="size-full wp-image-61706" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Blend mode example in Chrome Canary. <em>Image: Screenshot/Webmonkey</em>.</p></div>Chrome&#8217;s experimental Canary channel and Safari&#8217;s WebKit nightly builds both <a href="http://blogs.adobe.com/webplatform/2013/04/23/all-blend-modes-for-css-fragment-shaders-have-landed/">now support all of the Photoshop-inspired blend modes</a> for CSS Shaders, part of Adobe&#8217;s effort to <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/09/adobes-css-shaders-now-an-official-web-standard/">bring Photoshop-style filter tools to the web</a>.</p>
<p>To see the new blend modes in action, grab a copy of the <a href="https://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/browser/canary.html">latest Chrome Canary</a> or <a href="http://nightly.webkit.org/">WebKit nightly builds</a>, enable the CSS Shaders option in <code>about:flags</code> and point your browser to Adobe&#8217;s <a href="http://codepen.io/adobe/pen/nygsD">sample code over on Codepen</a>. Previously, CSS Shaders <strike>required a special build of WebKit</strike> [<b>Update</b>: As Adobe's Alan Greenblatt points out in the comments, CSS shader support has been in Chrome stable since v25 (you still need to enable the flag). But if you want to play around with these new blend modes then you'll need Canary (or a WebKit nightly).]</p>
<p>The new blend mode support is part of Adobe&#8217;s CSS Shaders proposal, which <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/09/adobes-css-shaders-now-an-official-web-standard/">recently became part of the W3C&#8217;s CSS Filter Effects specification</a>. There are two types of shaders in the spec, CSS fragment shaders, which provide features similar to what Photoshop&#8217;s blending modes offer, and CSS vertex shaders, which handle the 3D animation filters we&#8217;ve <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2011/10/adobe-proposes-new-standard-for-3d-effects-on-the-web/">showcased in the past</a>.</p>
<p>The blending modes currently available include all the familiar options you&#8217;ll find in Adobe Photoshop, such as multiply, screen, overlay, luminosity and other photographer favorites.</p>
<p>For more details and links to the corresponding specs, be sure to check out <a href="http://maxvujovic.blogspot.com/2013/04/all-blend-modes-for-css-custom-filters.html">this post</a> from Max Vujovic, who is working on the CSS Filters implementation in WebKit and Blink.</p>
<p>As the CSS Filter Effects specification progresses through the standardization process (and stabilizes), hopefully other browsers will add support as well. </p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/experimental-css-shaders-bring-photoshop-filters-to-the-web/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>First Firefox OS Developer Phones Sell Out</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/first-firefox-os-phones-sell-out/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/first-firefox-os-phones-sell-out/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 14:48:22 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61692</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[Mobile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Firefox OS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internal]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/geeksphone-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/geeksphone.jpg" alt="First Firefox OS Developer Phones Sell Out" /></div>The first Firefox OS phones hit the market today and have already sold out. The two models available were not even aimed at consumers. Instead these are developer preview devices for those who'd like to get a jump on building apps for Firefox OS. Clearly quite a few developers want to do just that. Geeksphone, the manufacturer of the two phones, is hoping to have more available for sale later this week.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled -->
<p><div id="attachment_61696" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 590px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/geeksphone.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/geeksphone.jpg" alt="" title="geeksphone" width="580" height="294" class="size-full wp-image-61696" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The Firefox OS-based Geeksphone. <em>Image: Screenshot/Webmonkey</em>.</p></div>The first Firefox OS-powered mobile devices, manufactured by the Spanish company <a href="http://www.geeksphone.com/">Geeksphone</a>, went on sale today. Unfortunately for anyone hoping to get their hands on some hardware explicitly designed for Firefox OS, the phones have apparently <a href="http://shop.geeksphone.com/en/#buy-it">already sold out</a>.</p>
<p>For the average user that&#8217;s probably a good thing. Despite being a 1.0 release on real hardware these phones are not, <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2013/04/geeksphone-to-start-selling-firefox-os-developer-preview-phones/">according to Mozilla</a>, ready for prime time. </p>
<p>Instead these devices are intended for developers looking to build and test applications for Firefox OS. And clearly there&#8217;s a lot of interested developers. That&#8217;s not terribly surprising given that apps for Firefox OS are built using web basics, like HTML, CSS and JavaScript, which means anyone who can build a website can build a Firefox OS app.</p>
<p>Indeed, thanks to the <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/12/new-simulator-showcases-mozillas-coming-firefox-os/">Firefox OS simulator</a> there are already quite a few Firefox OS apps available. But while the simulator is helpful, it&#8217;s just not the same as testing on an actual device. Having actual hardware allows developers to &#8220;test the capabilities of Firefox OS in a real environment with a mobile network and true hardware characteristics like the accelerometer and camera,&#8221; <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2013/04/geeksphone-to-start-selling-firefox-os-developer-preview-phones/">writes</a> Stormy Peters, Mozilla&#8217;s Director of Developer Engagement.</p>
<p>While Geeksphone may be the first company to produce an actual Firefox OS phone (albeit a &#8220;developer preview&#8221;), Mozilla has some more familiar hardware makers lined up to produce consumer devices, including Sony, LG and Alcatel, all of which have signed up to turn out Firefox OS mobile phones.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s still no official word on when these manufacturers will be joining the Firefox OS party, but Mozilla&#8217;s plan is to have a more polished version of its OS out in the next few months, with official releases in Brazil, Venezuela, Portugal, Spain and Poland over the next several months.</p>
<p>One of the Geeksphone devices is on its way to the Webmonkey lair, so we&#8217;ll give you the lowdown on what it&#8217;s like to develop for Firefox OS as soon as we get a chance to play with it. In the mean time, if you missed out on the Geeksphone today the company is hoping to have more available for sale later this week. Alternately, you can always <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/Firefox_OS/Building_and_installing_Firefox_OS">install Firefox OS on your own device</a> or just use <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/12/new-simulator-showcases-mozillas-coming-firefox-os/">the Firefox OS simulator</a>.</p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/first-firefox-os-phones-sell-out/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>1</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Web&#8217;s Most Popular JavaScript Library Drops Support for Older Versions of IE</title>
        <link>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/webs-most-popular-javascript-library-drops-support-for-older-versions-of-ie/</link>
        <comments>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/webs-most-popular-javascript-library-drops-support-for-older-versions-of-ie/#comments</comments>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 17:29:24 +0000</pubDate>

                <dc:creator>Scott Gilbertson</dc:creator>

        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.webmonkey.com/?p=61677</guid>
        		<category><![CDATA[JavaScript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jQuery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[External]]></category>
            <enclosure url="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/ievoodoodoll-200x100.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="48000" />
                    <description><![CDATA[<div class="rss_thumbnail"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/ievoodoodoll.jpg" alt="Web&#8217;s Most Popular JavaScript Library Drops Support for Older Versions of IE" /></div>The jQuery framework has hit a huge milestone, version 2.0. This release may be most notable for what's not in it -- namely support for Internet Explorer 6, 7 and 8. If you're a jQuery fan, but you need to continue supporting old versions of IE, fear not, jQuery 1.9 will continue to be supported for some time to come.]]></description>

            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!-- wpautop enabled -->
<p><div id="attachment_61682" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="width: 310px"><a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/ievoodoodoll.jpg"><img src="http://www.webmonkey.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/ievoodoodoll.jpg" alt="" title="ievoodoodoll" width="300" height="290" class="size-full wp-image-61682" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">IE voodoo doll by <em><a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/volantra/3406410663/">Cheryl Brind</a>/Flickr</em>.</p></div>The popular jQuery JavaScript library has hit a major milestone with the <a href="http://blog.jquery.com/2013/04/18/jquery-2-0-released/">release of jQuery 2.0</a>. The 2.0 release is some 12 percent smaller than its predecessor, but the big news is that jQuery 2.0 drops support for Internet Explorer 6, 7 and 8.</p>
<p>Created to simplify the process of writing JavaScript and manipulating HTML, jQuery began life a mere seven years ago, but quickly found favor with developers sick of dealing with cross-browser JavaScript hassles. According to one <a href="http://www.webmonkey.com/2012/08/survey-finds-jquery-library-running-on-half-of-all-websites/">survey published last year</a>, jQuery turns up on roughly half of all sites on the web.</p>
<p>Will dropping support for older versions of IE change that? Probably not. If your site needs to maintain support for IE 8 and below (or even IE 9 and 10 running in compatibility mode) you&#8217;ll just need to stick with jQuery 1.9 or below. </p>
<p>&#8220;jQuery 2.0 is intended for the modern web,&#8221; <a href="http://blog.jquery.com/2013/04/18/jquery-2-0-released/">writes</a> jQuery&#8217;s Dave Methvin on the Query Foundation website. &#8220;We&#8217;ve got jQuery 1.x to handle older browsers and fully expect to support it for several more years.&#8221;</p>
<p>If you want the best of both worlds you can <a href="http://blog.jquery.com/2013/04/18/jquery-2-0-released/">use a conditional comment</a> to serve 2.0 to newer browsers and 1.9 to older ones, but the far easier way to go is sticking with jQuery 1.x. For now at least the primary use case for the 2.0 line is situations where IE support isn&#8217;t a consideration &#8212; think Chrome or Firefox add-ons, PhoneGap apps or node.js. </p>
<div id='linker_widget' class='contextly-widget'></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <wfw:commentRss>http://www.webmonkey.com/2013/04/webs-most-popular-javascript-library-drops-support-for-older-versions-of-ie/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
        <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>

        
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
